"I understand that life is meaningless."
For you to say
life is meaningless is incorrect.
Formlessness does not mean futility.
It's a mere expression of an objective,
scientific fact.
It means that nothing is eternal
or unchanging.
Everything in this world changes.
All matters in the material world change.
Matters arise, dissolve
and then return to emptiness.
All bodies and living things also change.
Life arises, ages, gets sick and dies.
Our minds also change.
It arises, abides, changes and vanishes.
There are no things that are permanent,
eternal, or unchanging.
All beings are endlessly changing.
Change is nature's true law.
Yet, we mistakenly think
that there are things that don't change.
Because we think there are eternal things
that last forever, when things do change,
we suffer.
There is no reason to suffer over a change.
The only reason it becomes a suffering
is because you mistakenly think
things don't change, but they do.
Formlessness doesn't mean futility.
It's rather an objective truth.
It has nothing to do with futility.
There's no issue as long as
you consider change as natural.
But as you think that things don't change,
you start finding that your expectations
are not met. Hence you suffer.
"I can't relate to the phrase
that 'life is a dream'.
Why is it a dream? And if it is,
how can I awake from it?"
You said you understand
that life is formless. You have it wrong.
When we say life is formless,
it doesn't mean that life is meaningless.
Not only life but everything in this world changes. Every existing thing is impermanent.
When we say life is formless,
it doesn't imply that life is futile.
You shouldn't take this
as life not worth living for.
Why is not life unworthy of living?
Of course it's worthy.
You don't live life for a certain reason.
You just live.
If you're going to live,
you might as well live a good life
rather than a bad one, no?
Why not live a happy life
rather than an unhappy one?
Even if just for a day, you might as well
live a fun day. Why suffer?
We try to cling on to things,
yet can't get a hold of them.
Even when we think we have a hold,
times change and we don't.
When you realize this truth, you'll notice
there is nothing to be happy
about in gaining things
or sad about in losing things.
No need to get excited over new buds,
no need to cry over fallen leaves.
New buds are good in their own way,
so are falling leaves.
The phrase "Life's a dream" doesn't mean
that life is futile. It doesn't indicate
that life is pointless.
Let's assume you're running away
from a robber in your dream.
You wake up, there is no robber.
It was a figment of your imagination,
it wasn't real. It was a dream, a fantasy.
In the same way, when we say
this person is bad or good,
that something is right or wrong,
it's not real.
It's only an image derived
from your karma.
Don't conclude that it's reality.
Just as a dream isn't real, it isn't.
The way we judge things as right or wrong
is nothing but a dream. It isn't real.
It's only a picture that your mind created.
Hence it's not worth obsessing over.
Just as a dream is a fantasy once awake,
our judgments are nothing but a dream.
And just as we think dreams are real
and break out into sweats
while running away in our dreams,
we're caught up in illusions
that our mind's have created,
and we struggle with them.
Hence I'm saying, wake up
from your illusions,
as you awake from a dream.
Living itself is not a dream,
but how we judge things are right or wrong,
correct or incorrect, happy or sad
are all created within our minds.
It's as if we meet a robber
or a savior in a dream.
Once we're awake, neither a sweet dream
nor a nightmare is real.
In the same way, as you detach
from such images of the mind,
they are nothing
but fantasies and illusions.
Once you break free from them,
you no longer have to live
with such sufferings.
Look at me.
From your perspective,
do I look like I have sufferings?
To you, I probably don't look like I do.
What's there to suffer over?
I have no parents, no kids,
no wife, no possessions.
How free must I appear?
And yet in my head,
I have my own kind of sufferings.
I worry about the famine in North Korea,
kids in India, and those in Afghanistan.
I have all sorts of worries.
Your worries are limited
to your own household, aren't they?
And yet I'm worried about our country,
our world, the environment.
Hence from my perspective,
your worries aren't that big of a deal.
And yet what do you say?
You'd think I'm taking on
unnecessary worries for myself.
I look at you the same way.
I don't think you have any problems.
Did you have breakfast this morning?
Did you have lunch here?
Are you going to have dinner?
Are you not wearing clothes?
Do you not have a place to sleep?
What's your problem then?
You can afford three meals a day
wherever it may be.
You have nothing to worry about.
And yet in your mind, you carry
the whole world's weight on your shoulders.
This is an illness you're creating
for yourself within your mind.
You're here listening to dharma
and laughing today.
But it's possible that you see a doctor
tomorrow and find out you have cancer.
Did the cancer appear all of a sudden?
Did you not have it
while you were here laughing?
You had it all along. It's all in the mind.
Cancer did not cause suffering,
your mind caused you pain and suffering.
If you have cancer but don't care,
it's not a problem.
Even without cancer, you can still
lose sleep over the possibility of it.
And what if the doctor gets it wrong?
You'd spend days thinking
you're going to die over nothing.
Therefore it's all in your mind.
Hence we say life is like a dream.
Just as you awake from a dream,
you should awake from illusions.